<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the Lord Digbies speech in the House of Commons; to the bill of attainder of the Earle of Strafford, the 21th. of Aprill. 1641. Written by occasion of the first publishing of that speech of his Lordships. And now printed in regard of the reprinting of that speech.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E198_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859009</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859009</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111070</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75434)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111070)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 35:E198[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the Lord Digbies speech in the House of Commons; to the bill of attainder of the Earle of Strafford, the 21th. of Aprill. 1641. Written by occasion of the first publishing of that speech of his Lordships. And now printed in regard of the reprinting of that speech.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: The Lord Digbies speech in the House of Commons. To the bill of attainder, of the Earle of Strafford, the 21 of April, 1641.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bristol, George Digby, --  Earl of, 1612-1677. --  Lord Digbies speech in the House of Commons. To the bill of attainder, of the Earle of Strafford, the 21 of April, 1641 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, --  Earl of, 1593-1641.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111070:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO THE LORD <hi>DIGBIES</hi> Speech in the Houſe of COMMONS; To the Bill of Attainder of the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> the 21<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>April.</hi> 1641. Written by occaſion of the firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of that ſpeech of his Lordſhips. And now printed in regard of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing of that <hi>Speech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111070:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111070:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER To the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> Speech in the Houſe of COMMONS. To the Bill of Attainder of the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> the 21. of <hi>April.</hi> 1641.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE intereſt which every good ſubject hath in the actions of the King and State, is ſufficient to defend him from the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of being a buſie body in maintaining the Juſtice of them. That, and my deſire to doe the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> ſervice, by endeavoring to give him ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in thoſe ſcruples, which made him differ from his former ſelfe, have moved me to enter into an examination, of the grounds of that change which his Lordſh. hath declared in his ſpeech to the Bill of Attainder of the Lord <hi>Strafford.</hi> They are but two.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:111070:3"/>
            <p>The firſt and maine is the fayling of that in the proofe, which induced his Lordſh. to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that it was fit the Lord of <hi>Strafford</hi> ſhould be accuſed of Treaſon, which was, his adviſing the King to imploy the Army of <hi>Ireland</hi> to reduce <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For admitting the circumſtances of Maſter Secretary <hi>Vanes,</hi> three ſeverall examinations at the Preparatory Committee, to be the ſame his Lordſhip hath reported, yet why they ſhould prevaile ſo much with his Lordſhip, as to work to an utter overthrow of his evidence, as unto the Army of <hi>Ireland:</hi> I muſt confeſſe, I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot comprehend, becauſe all his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip doth, or would have others inferre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon is; <hi>That hee who twiſe upon oath, with time of recollection could not remember any thing of ſuch abuſines, might well a third time miſremember ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For certainely notes taken by Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> himſelfe, of words ſpoken by the Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> either at the time, and upon the place when, and where they were uttered, or ſoone after when they were freſh in memory, are a ſtronger confirmation that his remembrance at laſt fixed upon the point of truth; notwithſtanding the long trepidation about it, then the notes of any other Counſellor could have beene. And there was a time when his Lordſhip avoweth, that <hi>hee was fortified in his beliefe by the imagination that the notes hee had beene told of would have proved ſome other Counſellors.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111070:3"/>
            <p>So ſtrong indeed to my underſtanding, that I cannot ſee how the validity of Mr. Secretaries teſtimony can be in the leaſt degree infringed, without making a great breach into his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erce.</p>
            <p>For if I ſhould allow (which I doe not) that there could be <hi>no other uſe</hi> of committing thoſe <hi>venemous parts of diſcourſes</hi> to paper, but <hi>to accuſe men, and to bring them into danger,</hi> certainely it then behooved Mr. Secretary to bee very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that the notes he tooke were no ſuch <hi>diſioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fragments,</hi> as by falling into other hands, (as it hapned) might make a great Miniſter of ſtate, and his fellow Counſellor to bee thought to have ſaid that which was never intended by him.</p>
            <p>And if it betrue, as I rather beleeve, that Mr. Secretaries end in regiſtring that indeed tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly venemous adviſe of the Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> was to make ſure of his memory, in caſe hee ſhould ever be called to teſtifie what had paſſed at that Iunto (which hath alſo hapned;) it then beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him no leſſe to conſider well what hee put downe in writing, for the ſupport of his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and much more to recollect himſelfe very well before hee depoſed any thing in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his notes, after the paper was burnt. And conſidering his having at firſt raſhly ſaid, that hee could not charge the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> with that of the Iriſh Army, it was a great
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111070:4"/>providence of God, that a copy of the paper hee had burned ſhould have beene taken, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and atteſted in the manner it was, without his having had any hand in any of them. For I doe not know even what I ſhould have thought of Maſter Secretaries teſtimony with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this forraine helpe, although with it I think no ſingle teſtimony can be ſtronger, and that his had not beene ſo ſtrong, though hee had at firſt depoſed the ſame hee did at laſt, as it is now, notwithſtanding his variation, taking in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming circumſtances from without.</p>
            <p>I humbly beſeech the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> who I ſee hath a noble and Chriſtian care <hi>not to have any thing driven to an aſpertion on Master Secretary,</hi> firſt to thinke well upon the things I have now ſuggeſted to his conſideration, touching the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity which in duty lay on Mr. Secretary to take heed that there were not a ſyllable, nor title amiſſe in his notes, and then to tell himſelfe what place there is left; for imagining <hi>there might bee a miſtake of herefor there, or this for that, and that it is probable there was ſo, ſince it is confest on all hands, that the debate then was concerning a warre with Scotland.</hi> For that there was any ſuch miſtake in the copy of his notes, cannot be fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied without infinite injury to Mr. Secretaries ſonne, and to that moſt worthy Gentleman Maſter <hi>Pimme,</hi> who took the copie with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make the uſe hath beene made of it, and who, I heare, have in generall but high termes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111070:4"/>averred the truth thereof, having both had a ſight of the originall, and being both of untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and undoubted veracity. And that Maſter Secretary could not ſo miſtake in the making of his memoriall, is very manifeſt, by the incohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> Criticiſme with the whole context of the preceding words, <hi>viz. That having tryed the affections of his people, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie was looſe and abſolved from all rules of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and was to doe euery thing, that power would admit, and that his Majeſty had tryed all wayes, and was refuſed, and ſhould be acquitted, both with God and man; and that hee had an Army in Ireland, which hee might imploy to reduce this Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what need was there to make ſo great a Muſter of things done in England, for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting of his Majeſtie with God, and man; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the employing of the Iriſh Army, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Kingdome of Scotland.</p>
            <p>And though the primary debate of that day was concerning a warre with Scotland, yet that debate muſt needs bring in a ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> how monies might be raiſed in England towards the making of that warre, the Parliament having refuſed to ſupply his Majeſtie, as the Lord <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> moſt wickedly ſlaundered the houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>And if in the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> conceit, it were not hard for Mr. Secretary to miſtake in the manner aforeſaid, then why was his Lordſhip ſo eaſily engaged to proſecute his accuſation of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111070:5"/>the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> of high Treaſon, with ſo much earneſtneſſe, founding his judgement on a Baſis that might ſo eaſily faile, and which by the wavering of Mr. Secretary in his teſtimony hee had cauſe to feare would faile; nay which had already actually fayled ſo farre, that there was no expectance of more then a ſingle teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony fortified with circumſtances, ſome time before his Lordſhip gave over his <hi>former fervor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if it ſhould bee admitted, that there is no improbality of ſuch an unwilfull miſtake in Mr. Secretary <hi>Vane,</hi> then it cannot be denyed, but that an other Counſellor of that Iunto might as eaſily have committed the ſame, or the like er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his notes; and allowing me this, I ſhall then beſeech his Lordſhip without prejudice to Mr. Secretary, to give himſelfe a good reaſon, why <hi>that ground of his accuſation, that ſpurre of his proſecution, that baſis of his Iudgement of the Earle of Strafford as unto Treaſon, ſhould be quite vaniſht away to his underſtanding,</hi> ſo ſoone as hee knew the notes were Sir <hi>Henry Vanes,</hi> which till that inſtant had beene in ſuch force of beliefe with him, that <hi>had it remained in the ſame, hee ſhould not have beene tender in the Lord</hi> Straffords <hi>condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For in the ſcales of my weake Iudgement there is no ſuch difference in the weight of two Counſellors notes, eſpecially thoſe which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be Mr. Secretary <hi>Vanes,</hi> having beene at laſt, though ſlowly confirmed by his memory upon oath, without helpe of his paper; whereas
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111070:5"/>thoſe of ſome other Counſellors might have proved inferior in thoſe two great credentiall circumſtances, for ought his Lordſhip had then heard, or had reaſon to imagine.</p>
            <p>For it will not helpe his Lordſhip to ſay, that hee hath expreſſed himſelfe in thoſe wary termes, that to his underſtanding that ground is <hi>quite vaniſht away, as unto Treaſon,</hi> toward the legall proofe whereof a ſingle witneſſe is no better then none; becauſe no notes could have ſupplyed the defect of another witneſſe, and all the reſt of the Iunto had already upon their oathes remembred nothing of this matter. Before his Lordſhip changed his judgement, and for ought hee could know, might have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to doe ſo, not withſtanding the production of any of their notes, which they upon their re-examination might alſo have evaded, as his Lordſhip would theſe of Mr. Secretaries.</p>
            <p>So that upon the whole matter had this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of the Iriſh Army beene the ſole charge, and proved no otherwiſe then his Lordſhip ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined it would have beene, that is to ſay by Sir <hi>Henry Vanes</hi> ſingle teſtimony without his notes, and ſome other Counſellors nores without his teſtimony, I cannot ſee how his Lordſhip could judiciouſly have condemned the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> of treaſon with innocence according to his plin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
            <p>And as for a diffuſing of a complexion of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon over all, if that particular had beene ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111070:6"/>witneſſed, or becomming a With to bind all the ſcattered and leſſer branches, as it were into a faggot of Treaſon, Sure the antecedent words are ſo much more powerfull to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as they are more comprehenſive, and they were clearly depoſed by my Lord the Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> as well as by Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> though no other of the Iunto remembred any thing of them neither, which doth take off much of the ſtrangeneſſe of Mr. Secretaries ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle teſtimony, and I beleeve hath bin the ground whereupon many a tender conſcience hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that Bill, wherein his Lordſhip was more ſcrupulous then I canyetfind ſufficient cauſe for.</p>
            <p>For I crave leave to aske his Lordſhip this Queſtion, whether, if ſome miſcreant had been tampering with others to take away the life of the King, and this had beene evidenced by two witneſſes, whereof one had depoſed, that hee adviſed the doing of it by poyſon as the ſureſt and ſafeſt way, the other denying thoſe words upon oath, ſhould notwithſtanding have ſworn clearely that hee heard him perſwade the killing of the King, and giving reaſons for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and lawfulneſſe thereof, and his Lordſhip had beene one of the Iury, whether hee would have made any more bones of condemning that villany, then if they had both agreed in a tale touching the matter of poyſon: And if his Lordſhip could have ſwallowed that difference in their depoſitions well enough, it may then be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111070:6"/>a matter worthy of his further enquiry, from what quarter that Gnat came, which ſtuck ſo faſt with his Lordſhip in a caſe fully paralell: There reſting as little doubt in one that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty might lawfully have imployed the Iriſh Army to reduce this kingdome, if he might, and was to have done every thing that power would admit for the raiſing of monies otherwiſe, after the Parliament had not ſupplyed him, as there would have reſted in another, whether he might have poyſoned the King, after he had been ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that he might have killed him.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> ſaw very well, that the knot of the With was in this part of that deſperate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe of his, and the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> may remember the poor ſhift he made to looſe it by explaining himſelfe thus. His Majeſty <hi>was to doe every thing that power would admit, that is every thing that power would lawfully admit,</hi> to the doing wherof I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Majeſty needed not to be looſed, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from all rules of government. And ſo for thoſe other words in the end of the 22. Article, that his Majeſty ſhould firſt try the Parliament here, and if that did not ſupply him according to his occaſions, he might then uſe his prerogative as he pleaſed to leavy what he needed, &amp; that he ſhould be acquitted both of God and man, <hi>if he tooke ſome other courſes, though it were againſt the will of his ſubjects.</hi> And the declaration he made in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen counſell mentioned in the end of the 21 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle. That he would ſerve his Majeſty <hi>in any other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111070:7"/>way</hi> in caſe the Parliament did not ſupply him; <hi>that is lawfull way, and lawfull courſes,</hi> ſaid the Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> now he found the point of theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous words turned upon himſelfe. And yet there was a time when no man urged with more vehemencie, that no ſuch Prerogative courſes to raiſe monies could be lawfull; and I am ſure no lawfull courſes at any time would have beene againſt the wills of any of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſubjects.</p>
            <p>This was all that the mighty wit of the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> could deviſe in avoydance of the ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing guilt of that moſt treacherous, and wicked Counſell of his. But the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> helpeth him with many better guards.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by profeſſing that he can have no noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any bodies intent to ſubvert the Lawes treaſonably, but by force. What a wide doore hath his Lordſhip in few words ſet open to wicked Iudges and Counſellors, to trample the publike liberty of Kingdomes and States under foot, and then to eſcape without puniſhment, or with leſſe then can reſtraine them; or ſecure others from their lewd practiſes. May not their concurrence and conſtancy in giving ſuch wicked judgements, &amp; counſels upon all emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſions, be as ſure evidences of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents to ſubvert the Lawes, as the readineſſe of ſword-men to abet and maintaine them therein. May not a free mighty Monarchy be thus in an age, or two, quietly converted into a moſt ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111070:7"/>and impotent tyrannie, by the pen, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of the ſword of Iuſtice, without the uſe of any other on the Princes part, if the Lawes of the land, and of the Religion profeſſed in it, bind the people from drawing their ſwords in maintenance of their liberty? and ſhall their obedience to God, and the King, and their Lawes, leave them without hope or means of redreſſe by the ſame Lawes or what ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent redreſſe, and reparation can be made then if the reſult of a hundred ſuch wicked judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Counſels ſhall be onely <hi>a great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour, and a hundred miſdemeanors cannot make a felony; nor a hundred Felonies amount to a Treaſon,</hi> according to the Lord <hi>Straffords</hi> poſition maintained publikely at his tryall: I wiſh the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> had longer ruminated upon his ill digeſted judgement in this point, before he put it over for good.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the next words. They are. <hi>And this deſigne of force not appearing, all his other wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked practiſes cannot amount ſo high with me.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if by <hi>this deſigne</hi> his Lordſhip meane the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular deſigne of bringing the Iriſh Army into <hi>England,</hi> then is the conſequence moſt inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. For ſure if the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> had not, he might have had ſome other deſigne upon this Kingdome, that would have amounted to hight treaſon in the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> eye: or if <hi>by this deſign</hi> his Lordſhip intend generally the deſigne of uſing force, then ſure it was made plaine enough
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111070:8"/>to his Lordſhip at the tryall, that <hi>the Lord Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford did more then deſigne the uſing of force</hi> to the ſubverſion of more then one of the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> having actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally levied warre upon the Kings liege people, to conſtraine obedience to his illegall ſummons and orders upon Paper-petitions, and to raiſe moneys upon them againſt their wills.</p>
            <p>But his Lordſhip ſaith, <hi>Hee can find a more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſpring from whence to derive thoſe, and all his other Crimes then from an intention to bring in Tyranny, and to make his owne poſterity, as well as ours ſlaves. As from revenge, from pride, from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, from paſsion, from inſolence of nature.</hi> Is it poſſible that ſo ſharpe a wit as the Lord <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes,</hi> that can ſo quickly eſpy the miſhap of any argument brought forth againſt the Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> ſhould not ſee this miſconception of his own in his excuſe? Shall no man be a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that can find another more naturall, ſpring from whence to derive his treaſonable deſignes and actions, then from an intent to commit Treaſon? Then the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> would not have beene a Traytor with the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> though hee had brought the Iriſh Army into <hi>England,</hi> if that action had originally flowed from one of the foreſaid Springs, as I beleeve it would have done. Then his Lordſhip may abſolve many, and I am ſure will one of the Gun-powder Traytors, whoſe ſon hath found ſo much Princely compaſſion and favour from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111070:8"/>his Majeſtie, and the King his Father, upon (I beleeve) a well-grounded opinion, that the Fathers deſigne to have deſtroyed the King his Maſter, proceeded not from any malicious mind to his ſacred perſon, but was derived from his zeale to his Religion, a purer ſpring then any of thoſe his Lordſhip hath found out, to waſh the Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> which certainly have beene the ſprings of all the fowleſt treaſons in the world.</p>
            <p>And as for the Lord <hi>Straffords</hi> reſpect to his poſteritie, ſince the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> knoweth (no man better) that we are all deceived with a ſhew of good in every ſinne we are drawne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by him, who (hee thinketh) <hi>gave the Lord Strafford the application of his rare abilities:</hi> And that not only many Miniſters of State are eaſily engaged to bee Inſtruments of overthrowing the Common-wealth, and glory of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, ſo they may advance themſelves and their Families to riches and honour, becauſe that in ſo doing they imagine they get more in their private fortunes then they loſe in their parts of the publike; But even the wiſeſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces themſelves have by this deceit been drawne into the ſame errour, as <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh of <hi>France,</hi> (For an error it was in them, and may bee demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have been ſo, as farre as Politique mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are capable of demonſtration.)</p>
            <p>Nay ſince the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> avoweth that the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111070:9"/>conſideration of his poſteritie did not hold the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> himſelfe from becomming <hi>the grand Apostate to the Common-wealth, not only in opinions, but by falling from them to practiſes, as high, as tyrannicall, as any ſubject ever ventured on, and ſuch as made him the moſt dangerous Minister, the moſt inſupportable to free ſubjects that can bee Charactered;</hi> I know not why his Lordſhip ſhould eſteeme it ſo ſure a preſervative againſt the Treaſon he hath ſuffered for.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt ſaid juſtly, and ſo doth his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; <hi>For he doth not ſay, but the Lord Strafford was worthy to dye, and perhaps worthier then many a Traytor. He doth not ſay but his words, counſells, and actions, have beene proved to be ſuch as may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the King and Parliament to enact, that the like ſhall be Treaſon for the future, but only prayeth God to keepe him from giving judgement of death on any man, or of ruine to his innocent poſterity upon a Law made a</hi> Poſteriori. So that if his Lordſhip may be freed from this ſcruple of Conſcience, there is hope that hee may change his opinion, and be brought <hi>a Poſteriori;</hi> to declare his agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in judgement with himſelf, and the ſo much greater part of the Houſe of Commons. And that I ſhall now hope to doe by ſhewing him a fallacy in the ſecond, and laſt ground of his Argument.</p>
            <p>The fallacy lyeth in this, that his Lordſhip doth divide thoſe things in his conſideration which God hath joyned, and in doing this, will
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111070:9"/>needs be wiſer then the State, and Lawes hee liveth under, which no man ought to be, unleſſe they thwart the Law of God. This hee doth where he faith: <hi>There is in Parliament a double power of life and death by Bill, a Judiciall power, and a Legaſlative, that the meaſure of the one is what is legally just, of the other what is prudentially, and politiquely fit for the good and preſervation of the whole, but theſe may not be confounded in judgement, we may not piece up want of legallity with prudentiall fitneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly if his Lordſhip had but added theſe words, <hi>Except ſome Caſe as yet wholly omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or not yet ſufficiently declared, come to be judged in Parliament.</hi> I ſhould have fully aſſented to his whole diſcourſe in this point; But in either of thoſe Caſes to deny unto that repreſentative Body, the High Court of the Kingdome a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to doe any thing not unjuſt in it ſelfe (though not as yet legally declared to bee juſt) for the preſervation of that greater body it repreſents, when according to the ſincere, and diſpaſſionate judgement of Prudence, and Policy, it cannot be ſufficiently ſecured by Lawes already made, is neither agreeable to the Law of Nature, nor of the Land, nor of God, nor to a rule of his Lordſhips owne.</p>
            <p>Not to the law of Nature, which, in any caſe where the ſafety of the whole commeth into queſtion, doth not bind it ſelfe from ordering, in the great world, that light things ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111070:10"/>heavy aſcend. In the little, that the whole man upon conſultation ſhall conſent to the cutting off, of a gangren'd hand, or foot, though the former bee contrary to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, whereby elementall bodyes are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned in their motions; And the latter againſt that dictate of Nature, which inclineth each member to have a compaſſionate care of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of another ſo ſtrongly, that except in a like caſe, no part, nor the reſt of the whole may, nor can conſent to ſuch a mutilation.</p>
            <p>Not to the Law of the Land, For in that very Statute of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. whereby Treaſons were firſt declared, there is a paſſage which doth quite overthrow his Lordſhips diſtinction, and rules ſquared to his preſent purpoſe, as is yet plainer by divers ſubſequent ſtatutes if I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Engliſh, and there be no more but that, and a little right reaſon requiſite to underſtand Statute law, as there ought to bee. I will here tranſcribe the ſeverall paſſages, wherein I obſerve, that ſome or all of the latter Statutes are repealed, but that is not materiall to the purpoſe for which I cite them.</p>
            <p>25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>And becauſe that many other like Caſes of treaſon may happen in time to come, which a man cannot thinke nor declare at this preſent time: It is accorded, that if any other Caſe ſuppoſed Treaſon, which is not above ſpecified doth happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Juſtices, the Juſtices ſhall tarry without ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judgement of the Treaſon, till the Caſe be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111070:10"/>and declared before the King, and his Parliament, whether it ought to be judged Treaſon or Felony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>21. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>And that this Statute ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and hold place as well to them which be judged, or attainted for theſe foure points of the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in this preſent Parliament, as of them which ſhall be judged or attainted in the Parliament in time to time of any of the foure points of Treaſon afore ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>And that this ordinance extend as well to ſuch hurnings made after the firſt day of the raigne if our Soveraigne Lord the King till this time, as to burnings to be made in time to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>22. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>And that the ſaid</hi> Richard Rooſe, <hi>for the ſaid murther and poyſoning of the ſard two perſons, as is aforeſaid by authority of this preſent Parliament ſhall ſtand and bee attainted of High treaſon. And becauſe that deteſtable offence now newly practiſed and committed, requireth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment for the ſame. It is ordained and enacted by Authority of this preſent Parliament, that the ſaid</hi> Richard Rooſe <hi>ſhall therefore be boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to death.</hi> His offence was poyſoning a Pot of Pottage.</p>
            <p>By all which I conceive it to be elcere as the Noon-day, that the Parliaments of <hi>England,</hi> have heretofore as now, uſed to looke back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as well as forwards, if the occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it. And ſo, that his Lordſhips diſtinction, hath no ground in the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>And truly it hath is little in the law of God.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111070:11"/>For in that we reade, that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and all the Congregation, to whom the man that was found gathering ſticks on the Sabbath day was brought, at firſt indeed did only put him in ward, becauſe it was not yet declared what ſhould be done to him: But when it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, they then ſtoned that ſame man to death for that former fact by a Law made <hi>a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very ſame proceeding was held with the ſonne of the Iſraelitiſh woman, whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was an Egyptian for blaſpheming or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for he was alſo ſtoned to death <hi>a poſteriori,</hi> and a generall Law declared upon the occaſion, that as wel the ſtranger, as he that is borne in the Land, when he blaſphemeth the name of the Lord ſhall be put to death.</p>
            <p>This furniſheth an Anſwer to the Objection I have heard made to the former Inſtance, that the gatherer of ſticks on the Sabbath, was put to death by a ſpeciall direction from God, which may no more bee drawne into example now, then <hi>Abrahams</hi> going about to ſacrifice his Sonne.</p>
            <p>For, not to divert into that Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Declaration of God Almightie, ought to have beene a direction to the Jewes to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the breach of the Sabbath with death, which for ought appeares, was not ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by them, unleſſe <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> threatning, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.21. may be taken in that ſence. I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111070:11"/>conceive, that by the generality of the Law, which ordained, that Blaſphemy ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with death, it is plaine that the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Mungrell Egyptian Jew, for that ſinne was not extraordinary. And from both thoſe Inſtances, that by the example of the God of Heaven it is lawfull for the Aſſembly of Gods on Earth to put offenders to death for Crimes deſorving capitall puniſhment, though committed before they were declared to bee ſuch. And it may be, ſo much may alſo be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from that famous place, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.9.10. which I referre to further conſideration.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, his Lordſhips owne Rule in his ſpeech for the Tryenniall Parliament, is this, <hi>That the King out of Parliament hath a limitted, a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comſcribed Juriſdiction; But waited on by his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, no Monarch of the Eaſt is ſo abſolute in diſpelling grievances.</hi> For it is well knowne, that if any man how great ſoever doe once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a publique grievance, That is to ſay, A dangerous and inſupportable Miniſter to the State; thoſe Eaſterne Monarchs doe not uſe to ſtand upon punctilios of Lawes made, or to be made, no nor ſo much as upon the formality of legall proceedings, Wherein there hath beene more either right, or favour ſhewed to the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> by the King and his Parliament, then I beleeve ever was to any like Offender in the whole world before him, which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to his Majeſties, and their eternall glory and praiſe.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:111070:12"/>
            <p>I know well what may bee replyed by ſo me others, not by the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> of the dangerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this laſt mentioned doctrine of his, and am as ſenſible thereof as another man.</p>
            <p>But I doe humbly conceive, that there is yet more danger in the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> fore-rehearted doctrine: And that all that is in the laſt recited (being alſo as I take it more conformable to the Law of the Land) may be prevented by ſome good Ordinances, otherwiſe needful to be made, which is an Argument I muſt not digreſſe into here.</p>
            <p>In ſumme I hope ere this it is plaine, that in ſtead of the Prayer his Lordſhip made, it had beene more needfull for him, to have prayed to God to keepe him from making diſtinctions, where God himſelfe hath made none, which his Lordſhip knoweth is not well pleaſing to God, and muſt needs have obſerved to have beene the originall of many great diviſions, and combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions in the Church, and ſo might now have beene in this State, if God of his mercy, and by his over-ruling, power had not prevented it, contrary to his Lordſhips prudentiall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who I perceive would elſe have found a wrong Father for thoſe ſeared diſtractions of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Or if all I have yet ſaid bee not enough, let this ſuffice, that the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> himſelfe, not only in a former ſpeech made before he altered his mind, but in this very ſpeech doth clearely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111070:12"/>allow of this very kind of proceeding, which he would faine ſee me to diſallow.</p>
            <p>For after all the expreſſion of his ſo nice ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of conſcience in this point, even <hi>his Lordſhip</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>moved, that laying aſide the Bill of Attainder, the Houſe would thinke of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a one as might ſecure the ſtate from the Lord of Strafford, ſaving only his life.</hi> Which under fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour had not onely beene to condemne him <hi>a poſteriori</hi> to worſe then death, That is, either to have lived in perpetuall impriſonment, or to have become an ignominious fugitive, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond, after hee had beene branded by the Houſe of Commons, by his Lordſhip, and by his moſt ſacred Majeſtie in ſuch a manner, as might well have put the ſame thoughts into him, that every-one that met him would have killed him, which made <hi>Caine</hi> cry out, That his puniſhment was greater then he could beare; But for ought his Lordſhip hath expreſſed, the Bill he moved for, might have trenched as deep to the ruine of his innocent poſterity as the Bill of Attainder.</p>
            <p>Nay, I pray tell mee, how but by a Law <hi>a poſteriori</hi> could his Lordſhip have condemned the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> of high treaſon, as he hath profeſſed that hee ſhould and might have done with Innocence, if that of the Iriſh Army had beene proved to his underſtanding: For I doe not know whether as the caſe may bee put, <hi>thoſe words</hi> touching the Iriſh Army, had beene
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111070:13"/>treaſon, as yet declared by the Statute of 25. <hi>Edw</hi> 3. But it they be, then I am ſure the former words are a much vaſter treaſon.</p>
            <p>And to leave no leaſe of his Lordſhips de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence unventilated his reaſon drawne from the <hi>marking of a houſe infected with the plague</hi> being the ſame in other words with the Lo. <hi>Straffords</hi> taken from a boy, is of a little ſhew, but no force at all: For under favour, theſe compariſons ſhew no more, but that no action in it ſelfe indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, (ſuch as that the old Rhetoricians make uſe of, the going up to the top of the wals of a Towne of Garriſon) ought to bee made capitall to any man that had no knowledge of that Law, which I allow to bee good reaſon; But am ſure his Lordſhip will not allow, that the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> was charged with any ſuch ſlight Article, and much leſſe that the reſult of them all is a matter of indifference, or ſuch a one to which the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> could plead igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the hainouſneſſe of the crime: For there is no man capable of committing the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for which hee hath ſuffered, but muſt needs know, That as the ſafety of the people is the ſupreme Law, ſo the attempting to introduce any new forme of government, without their conſents, eſpecially an Arbitrary and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall one, is the greateſt wrong can be done, and the higheſt Treaſon can bee committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a State.</p>
            <p>And ſure Sir <hi>Thomas Wentworth</hi> who (as the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111070:13"/>Lord <hi>Digby</hi> himſelfe hath noted in his foreſaid ſpeech for the Trichniall Parliament was the man that whilome in the Houſe of Commons firſt moved for the inſerting of that clauſe in the Petition of Right <hi>And that your Majeſtie would bee alſo graciouſly pleaſed, for the further conmfort and ſafety of your people to declare your Royall will and pleaſure, that in the things aforeſaid all your Officers, and Miniſters ſhall ſerve you according to the Loves and Statutes of this Realme, as they tender the honour of your Majeſtie, and proſperity of this Kingdome</hi>) was not ignorant of the greatneſſe of this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: If the Lord <hi>Wentworth,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> were, as indeed a man may well thinke they were, that in their Story ſhall hereafter obſerve, that they no ſooner were admitted to the honour of being in the number of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Officers and Miniſters, but they began and ſo continued to bee the great tranſgreſſors and violaters of all the heads of the ſame Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Right, in the Kingdomes of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of moſt of them in both.</p>
            <p>I cannot obſerve any thing more in the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> ſpeech, that without wrong to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be thought to have beene a ground of his ſo ſolemne Proteſtation, that his vote went not to the taking away of the Lord <hi>Straffords</hi> life: But I have obſerved two paſſages which may give a little light, how his judgement, ſo neat in other things, came to bee corrupted in this.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:111070:14"/>
            <p>The firſt is an ungrounded apprehenſion, that <hi>neither the Lords nor the King would have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Bill, and conſequently, that the paſsing of it in the Houſe of Commons would be cauſe of great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in the State.</hi> For there is no paſſion doth multiply faſter, or which in ſhorter time will raiſe a greater miſt in the mind of a wiſe man then groundleſſe feare.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is; His Lordſhips having upon this occaſion <hi>much inculcated to his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the height and weight of the Crime of commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting murther with the ſword of Iuſtice;</hi> But for ought appeares in his Speech, having quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to put in a due Counterpoyſe thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, from a no leſſe ſerious conſideration of that ſaying of the Wiſe man; <hi>Hee that juſtifieth the wicked, and hee that condemneth the juſt, Even they both are abomination to the Lord.</hi> And the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident made upon King <hi>Ahab</hi> recorded in thoſe words; <hi>Becauſe thou haſt let goe out of thy hands a man whom I appointed to utter deſtruction, thy life ſhall goe for his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein notwithſtanding I would not be ſo underſtood, as if I who am a <hi>private man,</hi> did take upon me to judge of the Lord <hi>Staffords</hi> Cauſe. For, as I declared at the beginning, my intention throughout hath beene only to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the publike proceedings from ſcandall; and to cleare that Lord <hi>Digby</hi> from his ſcruples. The firſt of which now I have done with the zeale that became me, I ſhall henceforth with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111070:14"/>aequanimity expect to ſee what grounds there was of the Lord <hi>Straffords</hi> hopes, that hee may hereafter appeare leſſe guilty of the death hee died, then as yet he doth to me.</p>
            <p>And though in the later I have uſed neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry freedome in expreſſing my preſent conceits of the Lord <hi>Digbyes</hi> Reaſons, yet I reſerve a thought that the weakneſſe may bee in my own underſtanding, and that though of my ſelfe I am not, yet by his Lordſhip I may be made capable of them, being one that hath his eminent abilities in no leſſe admiration then any other whatſoever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
